<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Tourist_guide</string>
    <string name="title_activity_map">map</string>
    <string name="title_activity_login">LoginActivity</string>
    <string name="prompt_email">Email</string>
    <string name="prompt_password">Password</string>
    <string name="action_sign_in">Sign in or register</string>
    <string name="action_sign_in_short">Sign in</string>
    <string name="welcome">"Welcome !"</string>
    <string name="nuwaraeliya">"

Nuwara Eliya Sri Lanka (City of Lights) is a resort city in the Central Mountain Range of Sri Lanka. Blessed a with salubrious climate, breathtaking views of valleys, meadows, mountains and greenery; it’s hard to imagine that Nuwara Eliya is only 180 Km from the hot and humid Colombo.

Nuwara Eliya, also known as ‘Little’ England’, was the favorite hill station of the British who tried to create the resort into a typical English Village. The old brick Post office, country house like hill club, with its hunting pictures, mounted hunting trophies and fish, and it’s strict formal dinner attire; the 18 hole golf course, race course etc., evoke nostalgia of Colonial British Ceylon.
Lake Gregory

Lake Gregory is a picturesque, man-made Lake nestled at the bottom of small hills, bordering the town of Nuwara Eliya in Sri Lanka’s mountainous, tea-growing region. A visit or tour of Nuwara Eliya would not be complete without a visit to this scenic lake, with perhaps a boat ride or a walk along its shores. Originally a swamp and bog that was described by early residents as an “eye sore”, Lake Gregory was created by diverting the waters of the Thalagala stream which flows from the nearby Piduruthalagala mountain range.

The nearby town of Nuwara Eliya was “founded” by explorer Samuel Baker in 1846 and became a popular holiday spot for British colonials who wanted to get away from the sweltering heat of coastal cities and into the cool climes of the mountains. As the small town grew and expanded, the Governor of the time, Sir William Gregory, decided that electricity had to be introduced to the town and the Lake was originally created to generate much-needed electricity for the rapidly developing town.

Lake Gregory was fashioned under orders of British Governor Sir William Gregory in 1873. The water from the lake is directed to a place named “Blackpool” in Nuwara Eliya using a tunnel, and is used to generate electricity for the town even today. Lake Gregory also serves as an important catchment area for rainwater and mountain stream runoff, preventing flooding of the Nuwara Eliya town suburbs.

One of the benefits of the lake that was not foreseen by Governor Gregory was the recreational space it provided for the colonial holiday makers. Soon, boat rides on the lake became a favoured afternoon activity, a prelude to a picnic tea on the shores of the lake. Horse riding and pony rides for small children also became a popular activity on the shores of the Lake. It became a society icon, with “lake parties” becoming a trendy activity, and a walk to the lake from the racecourse was considered an invigorating activity for the energetic young people of the day. Of course, the muddy shores of the lake ensured that its popularity reigned with the ladies only during the warm, dry months of the year. The die-hard fishing and horse riding males, however, continued to use the lake year-round.

Lake Gregory continues to be a popular place for water-based activities including boat rides, sculling, fishing and paddle boating. Pony rides are still available for children, continuing the tradition started decades ago. Recent developments in the area have resulted in paved walkways being built along the lake, ensuring a comfortable walk as well as seating areas in scenic sites along the shoreline. Lake Gregory is also the landing site for the Air Taxis which fly into Nuwara Eliya from Colombo and Kandy.
Hakgala Botanical Gardens

The Hakgala Botanical Gardens is the second largest botanic garden in Sri Lanka and is located in a scenic part of Nuwara Eliya along the Badulla Road. Steeped in legend, often cloaked in a soft mist and always filled with colour and fragrance is the Hakgala Botanical Gardens, located around 10kms southeast of Nuwara Eliya. Tours to the gardens are a popular activity if holidaying in Nuwara Eliya, and while the Gardens are open year-round, the best time to visit and enjoy the beautiful blooms are from April to August, during the relatively dry and warmer period of year.

    The Botanic Garden lies under the Hakgala Peak, between 5000 – 6000 feet in elevation – the highest set Botanic Gardens in the world. Hakgala boasts 100-year-old Monetary Cypress trees from California, Japanese Cedars, Himalayan Pines and English Oak.

The Hakgala Botanical Garden span around 27 hectares and are built in a series of terraces, with natural streams flowing through it in several places. The Garden was originally created in 1861 by the British Colonial government under the curatorship of three British of the same name – William Nock, JK Nock and JJ Nock. to grow Cinchona – from which the anti-malaria medicine Quinine was extracted. Thereafter, as tea came to be a commercial crop in the mountainous region, the Gardens became an experimental tea growing area. In 1884 it began life as a Botanical Garden with a wide-ranging and systematic gathering of sub tropical and alpine plants from across the Commonwealth as well as experiments in acclimatising temperate-zone plants to a tropical climate.

Take a tour of the Gardens and be amazed at the variety of plants, estimated at over 10,000 different species. Here you will find a range of conifers and cedar trees from Australia, Bermuda and Japan; Cypress varieties from the Himalayas, China, Mexico and some pine trees from New Caledonia and the Canary Islands. Among the other famous trees in the Garden, there are a group of English Oak trees, introduced to the Garden in 1890 to commemorate the “Heart of Oak” official marching music of the Royal Navy. Among the successful adaptations of temperate trees to this sub tropical climate is a Camphor tree, which usually only grows at elevations of 12,000m.

Ancient mythology has a unique story as to its creation, from the epic tale the Ramayana. Hanuman, the monkey god, was sent to the Himalayas by Rama to bring back a specific medicinal herb. But he forgot what he was looking for, and decided to bring back a big chunk of the Himalayas, caught up in his jaw. The Gardens today rest at the foot of this huge rock called Hakgala (jaw-rock) which towers over the gardens and the surrounding Hakgala Nature Reserve.
Laxapana Falls (Lakshapana Falls)

Laxapana is one of Sri Lanka’s most famous waterfalls, and perhaps the one that has proven the most useful in terms of generating power to the country, the Lakshapana waterfall is located in Nuwara Eliya district in the country’s mountainous region.

The Laxapana Falls falls are 129m high and rise from the Laxapana estate and plunges into the Maskeliya Oya via Maoussakelle. The waters of this mountainous river are fast moving, rushing over huge boulders and rocks, gurgling across a multitude of small streams around the mountains before emerging as an awe-inspiring waterfall, especially during the monsoon season when the rivers are swollen and full.

Located along the pilgrim’s tour route to Adam’s Peak, Laxapana falls is a favourite stopping place for a rest, an open air meal or a quick bathe in the large natural pools formed in the valley below the falls. The pristine jungle that surrounds the waterfall, which falls across a sheer rock cliff face, adds to the picture-perfect quality of the environment. It’s considered Sri Lanka’s seventh highest waterfall and is part of the Laxapana reservoir, which generates hydropower from a number of power stations in the vicinity.

The name Laxapana is attributed with many origins: some versions take its literal meaning of “a thousand lamps” in sinhala, and the fact that this waterfall is part of a hydropower system that lights up many homes; others describe the name as meaning “a hundred thousand stones”, pointing to the rock and boulder strewn path that the water follows before it gushes out in a waterfall. One fact though can be agreed on – the old name for the waterfall was “veddah hiti ella” meaning, the waterfall where the Veddah lived. The Veddah, Sri Lanka’s indigenous people, perhaps had a small colony in this area and lived in the many caves and cliff dwellings in this mountainous area.
Lover’s Leap Waterfall, Nuwara Eliya

Most visitors to a country love to learn about local folk tales and nothing makes a good story like a love story. And so, as visitors on tour stop at one of Nuwara Eliya’s most famous landmarks, the stories of the sad end of an ill-fated romance begins. Lover’s Leap in Nuwara Eliya, Sri Lanka’s popular holiday town in the mountains, is a massive rocky cliff with a waterfall of the same name.

Its name is derived from the fate of a young couple who decided to be bound together forever by jumping off the cliff to their demise. But the romantic tale of what brought them to this point, or the manner in which they met their end are woven into a myriad stories, each changing with the storyteller or perhaps even the day on which you hear it. Whatever the reasons behind the lovers plunge, the name has stuck and the entire cliff is now named Lover’s Leap.

The Lover’s Leap waterfall is a breathtaking sight, falling to a height of 30m in a long, cascading sheet of water. Located on a tea estate, the Lovers Leap waterfall is only 2km from Nuwara Eliya town, making it the closest waterfall to the bustling holiday town and resulting in its popularity with visitors and tour groups alike.

The waters that feed this waterfall are said to originate on the southern end of the Pidurutalagala mountain range, Sri Lanka’s highest. The waters are taken to brew the famous Nuwara Eliya Beer. Access to the Lover’s Leap waterfall is off the Nuwara Eliya – Kandapola Road.


A visit to this estate, entrance from the road at the Ramboda end of Nuwara Eliya, is significant because it was here that the first thirty tea plants sent from China to Sri Lanka were planted by Mr. Laurence Oliphant, increasing his tea acreage to 100 acres.
"</string>

    <string name="yaala">"Yala National Park (also known as Ruhuna National Park) is located in the south eastern region of Sri Lanka and extends over two provinces of Hambantota district of southern province and Monaragala district in Uva province. The entrance to the park is at Palatupana, 12km from Kirinda. The distance from Colombo to the entry point of Palatupana is 305 km.

The gateway to Yala National Park is Tissamaharama. A 20 km drive via Kirinda takes the visitors to the Palatupana. At Palatupana, the well-designed visitor center provides the information to the tourists and assign a tracker to all incoming vehicles. The park provides jeeps with soft–tops which gives the opportunitiy to view wild life. Dawn and dusk bring about the best timing for Yala Safari tours in the Yala National Park . Being located in one of the arid regions of Sri Lanka, the Climate of Ruhuna National Park is usually hot and dry. The mean annual temperature is 27 Celsius, although in the dry season the temperature could go as high as 37 Celsius.

The rocky outcrops scattered over the park provides vantage points to enjoy the sprawling areas with Sri Lanka’s dry zone landscape: low scrub and woods. Stillmore, the southern border of the park being the south-eastern coast, the brackish lagoons and dunes enhances the distinctive charm of the Yala National Park.

Wildlife

Of all the National Parks in Sri Lanka, Yala National Park gives the best opportunity to witness Sri Lanka’s broad variety of wildlife: colorful painted stork in troops are seen perched at the shores of lagoon where the crocodiles too have chosen to doze off; lovely fantailed peacocks in their resplendent blues and greens parade about amidst the woods where monkeys hang, leap and chatter; in the bush jungle are the Elephants; crossing the tracks and wandering off into the thorny scrub jungle is the star attraction of the park: the leopard.

A total of 32 species of mammals have been recorded. The threatened species include sloth bear (Melursus ursinus), Leopard (Panthera pardus kotiya), elephant (Elephas maximus), water buffalo (Bubalus bubalis), Wild boar (Sus scrofa), spotted deer (Axis axis ceylonessis), sambar (Cervus unicolor) and golden jackal (Canis aureus).

Leopards

Sri Lankan leopards (Panthera Pardus Kotiya) are said to be a distinct sub-species from their Indian neighbors. Leopards can be seen throughout the park, though best period for enjoying the sights of leopards is during January to July.

Yala National Park’s Block 1, on the western side of the park, the only one of all five blocks open to the visitors, has recorded the highest density of leopards among the leopard populations scattered in the wildlife parks of Sri Lanka. These magnificent beasts have now much habituated to the encroachment of their domains by the humans in jeeps. Young males don’t betray any sign of disturbance; they seem confident roaming over the gravel roads tracks as well as the bush jungle during the day: the visitors enjoy to no ends, fine photographic opportunities to capture the magnificent beasts well focused at the close range.

Elephants

Nearby Lunugamvehera National Park serves as a corridor between Yala and Uda Walwe National Park. Yala is home to considerable population of elephants which varies seasonally. Dry season of May to August is the best period to see elephants.

Birdlife

Yala National Park is rich in birdlife and around 130 species have been recorded.Raptors include crested serpent eagle and white bellied sea eagle. Among the water birds attracted to the lagoons are Lesser Flamingo, Pelicon, Spoonbill, painted stork, rare black necked Stork, grey heron, purple heron, night heron and Darter.

During the north-east monsoon the lagoons are visited by thousands of migrating waterfowl, including Pintail, Garganey, Eurasian Curlew, Whimbrel and turn stone, which mix with the residents such as whistling duck, Yellow Wattled Lapwing, Red Wattled Lapwig and Great Stone Plover.The forest is home to Orange Breasted Green Pigeon, Hornbills, Flycatchers, including Asian Paradise Flycatcher, Barbets and Orioles.

Reptiles

Notable reptiles are Mugger Crocodile, which is abundant in the abandoned tanks, Estuarine Crocodile, found in the main rivers, and Common monitor. Other reptiles include Cobra and Russel’s Viper. A variety of Sea Turtle, Olive Ridley and Leatherback, of which Yala coast line is a major nesting ground.

Park Gates

    Katagamuwa Entrance [Gate 1]
    Palatupana Entrance [Gate 2]
    Galge Entrance [Gate 3 and 4]
"</string>
    <string name="horton">"Horton Plains and World's End
Horton Plains, Sri Lanka’s only national park declared a World Heritage Site, is an eerie highland plateau popular with hikers. A circular trail of 10 km length winds through cloud forests and open grasslands. Major attractions are scenic spots such as Baker's Falls and the two spectacular panoramic viewpoints called “Big World’s End” and “Litte World’s End”. Horton Plains, situated at an elevation of more than 2000 meters above sea level, is Sri Lanka’s only national park within the hill country and the only one where hiking  is permitted without ranger, though strict rules have to be observed within the national park boundaries."

        How to reach?

      By Air: You can fly to the Bandaranaike International Airport in Colombo from anywhere in the world.

By Road: The town of Nuwara Eliya usually serves as the point where most backpackers and travelers spend the night before starting early the next day to Horton Plains. The journey will take around two hours and is usually done in hired taxis or tuk-tuks. It is best to visit the park in a group of more than three people as the vehicle cost gets divided equally.

By Train: Horton Plains National Park in Ohiya is easily accessible from Haputale, Ella and Nanu Oya due to direct train services. There is a train station in the Ohiya village (10 KM away from the park entrance), another one is at Pattipola (highest railway station in Sri Lanka at around 6200 feet) on the way back to Nuwara Eliya from the park.  </string>
    <string name="sembu">"Sambuwatta Lake is a beautiful man-made reservoir located in Elkaduwa, Matale. The lake is bordered by Cambell’s Land forest reserve and situated at an elevation of 1,140 m. The misty and chilly atmosphere with pine trees and tea-covered slopes surrounding the lake make visitors feel relaxed and tranquil.

What puts the lake in the top as a leisure and family travel destination is the plethora of adventure activities available such as zip-lining, swan/motor boat riding, canoeing and hiking. Bathing and swimming in the lake, however, is not allowed since the lake is fairly deep (30 – 40 ft), there is a separate pool built for that purpose.
How to get there?

    From Kandy (30.6 km): [ Google Maps Directions ] [ Turning Point – Street View ]
    From Matale (21.8 km): [ Google Maps Directions ] [ Turning Point – Street View ]

The road leading to the lake (Sembuwatte Lake Road) off Wattegama – Elkaduwa – Matale road (B461) is not in a favourable condition, especially the stretch that lies beyond the factory. This narrow and winding road stretches about 04 km from the main road to the lake. About 03 km in, there is a dilapidated tea factory (Elakduwa Tea Factory) and a small office, where you should stop to buy tickets.

Long vehicles like 54 seat Leyland buses/Coaches should be parked here. Small vehicles can safely be driven beyond this point up to the lake and park at the lake premises. Owing to the narrowness of the road, it can be heavily congested during holidays.Tuk-Tuk drivers at the turning points try to dissuade people from getting their vehicles on to the lake road so that they can earn their buck. You should hear none of this since all sorts of vehicles travel upon this road daily.
Essential Information

    Ticket prices
        Locals: Rs 200
        Foreigners: Rs 1,000
    Opening Hours : 08:00 AM – 05: 00 PM
    Accommodation
        Polo Bungalow :  Rs 15,000  ( 12 pax)
        The Summer huts:
            Rs 1000 per person in a group of  min 10 pax
            For a group less than 10 pax: Rs 7,500"</string>
    <string name="ella">"Located in the vast tea plantations of Sri Lanka’s cultural center, Ella is one of the most popular places to visit in Sri Lanka. Because of this, Ella was at the top of our Sri Lanka bucket list, and even with such high expectations, we weren’t disappointed!

We fell in love with the place during our visit – partly because of the vast variety of fun things to do in Ella! From short hikes to lessons on Sri Lankan tradition, our time in Ella was fun and memorable!

For first-time visitors, it can be hard to know exactly what to do. Especially when the most famous attraction in Ella, the Nine Arch Bridge, only takes an hour to visit.

So in this blog, we’re going to share with you the 17 best things to do in Ella, Sri Lanka. So you can not only see the famous bridge but also experience everything else this town has to offer."
    1. Hike Little Adam’s Peak
        Just because it’s called Little Adam’s Peak doesn’t mean it’s any less amazing than the original Adam’s Peak – it’s just easier to get to! To reach the top of Little Adam’s Peak from Ella it takes around an hour, but if you want to shave some time off the hike then consider getting a tuk-tuk to the start of the trail at Ravana Zipline. From here, it’s only 20 minutes to the top.

Once you’re at the top you can then walk the ridgeline and explore. There are actually three peaks on Little Adam’s Peak and it takes around 30 minutes to reach the furthest one.

Due to safety reasons, I wouldn’t recommend hiking to the last peak if you’re traveling with children. It gets very narrow and steep!

    2. Visit th famous Nine Arch Bridge for Sunrise
        Arguably the most famous attraction in Ella is the Nine Arch Bridge. This gorgeous bridge is surrounded by lush greenery and tea fields and has become the postcard of Sri Lanka. Although I’m sure, almost everyone visits the Nine Arch Bridge during their visit to Ella, very few go for sunrise.

To me, it’s such a shame because not only are there fewer people (sometimes none) but there are two trains in the morning – one at 6:15 am and then one at 6:40 am. There are lots more trains throughout the day including around 9:30 am, 11:30 am, 3:30 pm, 4:30 pm, and 5:30 pm, but none as close together as in the morning.

    3. Flying Ravana Zipline
        During the zipline, you can take in the stunning views around you as you zoom past the viewing deck of spectators. It’s also a dual zipline which means you can race your friend to the bottom or just sit back and enjoy the ride next to each other.

The Ravana Zipline costs $20 USD for an adult and $15 USD for a child. The zipline is located at the bottom of Little Adam’s Peak and is a great activity to pair with the hike.

Although not the craziest zipline in the world, I still really enjoyed the activity – especially for the price!
    </string>
    <string name="sinharaja">"Sinharaja Rain Forest (a UNESCO World Heritage Site), the last viable remnant of Sri Lanka’s tropical lowland rainforest spanning an area of 18900 acres is located within Sabaragamuwa and Southern provinces of the south-west lowland wet zone of Sri Lanka. Sinharaja is bounded by rivers on three sides. On the north, Sinharaja is bounded by the Napola Dola and Koskulana Ganga. On the south and south-west are the rivers Maha Dola and Gin Ganga. On the west are the river Kalukandawa Ela and river Kudawa Ganga. To the east of Sinharaja is an ancient footpath near Beverley Tea Estate and by the Denuwa Kanda.

Reaching Sinharaja Rain Forest

From Northern or western parts of the country you can reach Sinharaja Forest Reserve via Ratnapura, Kiriella, Kalawana, Weddala. From the South you can enter Sinharaja Rain Forest from Deniyaya. Coming form Hambantota, Udawalawe you can enter Sinharaja from Rakwana side.

Area of Sinharaja Rain Forest

The total area of the Sinharaja Forest Reserve is 18,900 acres or 7,648 hectares. It ranges in altitude from 300m to 1,170m.

Significance of Sinharaja Forest

SiThe Sinharaja Forest reserve is alsoome to over 50% of Sri Lanka’s endemic species of mammals and butterflies, as well as many kinds of insects, reptiles and rare amphibians.

Establishment of Sinharaja Forest Reserve

Most of the area of Sinharaha forest was originally declared a forest reserve under the Waste Lands Ordinance in 1875. In 1978, Sinharaja Rain Forest was included in the international network of biosphere reserves, established and maintained as part of UNESCO’s Man and the Biosphere (MAB) program. In October 1988, this reserve, together with a northeastern extension of it, was declared Sri Lanka’s first National Wilderness Heritage Area. In December 1988, the Sinharaja Biosphere Reserve became Sri Lanka’s first natural site to be added to the UNESCO World Heritage list.

Climate on Sinharaja Rain Forest

Meteorological records gathered from in and around Sinharaja over the last 60 years reveal the annual rainfall of Sinharaja Forest has ranged between 3614mm to 5006mm and temperatures from 19°C to 34°C. The highest rainfall is owing to two monsoons: south-west monsoons during May-July and the northeast monsoons during November-January.

Physical features

Sinharaja Rain Forest is a narrow strip of undulating terrain consists of a series of ridges and valleys drained by an intricate network of streams, which flow into the Gin Ganga on the southern boundary and Kalu Ganga, via the Napola Dola, Koskulana Ganga and Kudawa Ganga, on the northern boundary.

Nature trails of Sinharaja Rain Forest

The two main nature trails of Sinharaja Rain Forest are those lead to the peak of Moulawella and the peak of Sinhagala. Both of these nature trails begins at Kudawa Conservation Centre (KCC) are equally enjoyable and enlightening. The forest is densly crowded with tall trees growing in close proximity, but winding trails make the trekking. Small streams of crystal-clear cool water, that is home to a variety of fish, toads and crabs, crisscross the trails. And the mixed species of birds are seen in the canopy of the woods.

Sinhagala Nature Trail

Trail head: Entrance to the protected area, Kudawa Conservation Centre, Weddagala, Kalawana Trail end: Sinhagala Peak Length of the trail: 2.4 km Rise in elevation gain along the trail: 300m at Trail Head: 473m at Trail End Approximate time: 5-7 hours Hiking Season: Best months are December to April"</string>
    <string name="invalid_username">Not a valid username</string>
    <string name="invalid_password">Password must be >5 characters</string>
    <string name="login_failed">"Login failed"</string>
    <string name="title_activity_mpasss">mpasss</string>
</resources>